so this is the gidy manand Sut
again and this is on the perception of
danger and how to develop that here biku
having gone into seclusion reflects
meditates this body is a lot of pain
Dua a lot of danger in this body there
arise all sorts of illnesses such as eye
disease hearing disease Body Disease Etc
ear mouth disease no disease tooth tooth
ache stomach ache coughing
fainting diarrhea illness is born from the change
diarrhea illness is born from the change
of seasons illness is born from Pure
poor attention sudden illnesses yeah
heart attack poof yeah brain
aneurysms illnesses born from the result
of one's
actions hangovers cold heat hunger
hangovers cold heat hunger
thirst U excreting and urinating
he lives as one who sees the danger in
this body so he develops that perception
yeah because the body is always there in
the back of your mind you start to see
there it will be quite effortless
because it's always there it is a basis
for your experience so the clearer you
see there the clearer its nature and
characteristics just describe there will
become so by seeing by being mindful of
the body you're mindful of all these
things implicitly that could that's the
clarification and the contemplation that
sort of um rewrites the significance of
your body now for an undeveloped mind
the significance in the body is
something that's seen as mine it's
something that's seen as a basis for
pleasure it's something that's seen as a
basic to protect what's mine something
to protect from others as well to
protect from the elements you don't see
it as that upon which your life depends
and yet something that's not in your
control you see there something that
belongs to you something that is you
let's say like that so you want to
rewrite that significance by
contemplating the body forward really is
because as what I said if the body were
not truly subject to all these things
well there would be no problem and
certainly the contemplation would not be
necessary but because the body is truly
subject to these things contemplating it
then you could see it for what it is
because it truly is like that it's just
you're covering up you're covering up
those aspects because they are
unpleasant so when somebody dwells established
so when somebody dwells established
correctly in the perception of danger
it's not that doesn't mean he's
constantly going in just danger danger
danger no means he rewrote the
significance of that body that he sees
peripherally enduring as a basis for
this experience and it's implicit in it it
experience and it's implicit in it it
just just sits there in in as the way
the same way the body sits there all
these implications of what the body is
subjected to is there thus none of that
um none of that can be taken now is mine
because it's it's clearly seen as an
alien thing a bag of skin all of this
all this um subject to all these
ailments and so on it's like even if you
want to you couldn't take it as
yours it's fragile yeah it's just out of
your hands it's inaccessible to
you and those things are not it's not
like oh that might yeah well it one of
those things no yeah the might the might
aspect it's on the level of a a specific
ailment but the aspect of an ailment
is sure so like you know death is
possible in in the sense of what type of
how you might die but the fact that
you're liable to death that's not a
possibility that's the reality it's not
like oh I might die no you will die so
the might and how pertains to how you
will die but not to whether you will die
or not that's for sure how will I get
ill yeah there could be different ways
but one thing for sure you will at some
point as The Bu say one who think thinks
uh that he has Health he a
fool there is no Health it's just this
so the absence of specific illness means
you're still ill with the possibility of
illness at any given time just I'm I'm
not as ill today yeah is not as ill and
Ill yeah so health is just being less
ill it's like
that there's no it's not beautiful it's
just less ugly less ugly yeah it's the
same stuff
[Music]
so that's also that the whole you know
the famous contemplation of organs and
what the body consists of needs to be
done on the peripheral level with a
peripheral thought so to speak not
directly staring and looking at
it needs to be done on the level of
where you see your body as that kind of
inaccessible basis for your life for
your ownership for your attachments yet
it's not in your control and then that
basis that not in your control you start
contemplating as a bag of skin randomly
operating organs all of that in there oh
that's going to be felt even more as
something that's not in your control
even more impermanent even more
dangerous to take as
mind yeah it obviously goes coincide
with sub practice of the the
organs because you see all those things
are operating yeah they're together on their
operating yeah they're together on their
own what and you just there as a sort
of you know PA with it just looking at
it not being able to do anything about
it hope yet fully depending on it yeah
so the heart is beating and when is it
going to stop how does it stop the fact
that it's beating now means that
possibility of it stopping now is also
there but then you don't okay this body
is just illness waiting to happen I'm
going to die anyway so yeah no that's
what I mean if you take that as a
abstract sort of a direct sort of you
know figuring out finding answers and
explaining what the body is it's not
going to result in disp or very little
now you want to be again establish
mindfulness correctly being peripherally aware of
correctly being peripherally aware of
your body enduring there and then on
that level of that peripherally enduring
body start contemplating this things and
then passion will become
impossible so there's a difference
between explaining it and setting it up
as a contemplation that you're
perceiving here and now by being mindful
of the body you that's why you don't
even need to be ill in order to
contemplate this just the possibility of
being ill is already pertaining on that
body enduring their peripheral and it's
more than enough to set the whole
context of this passion and danger
towards things that you would get on
account of a healthy body that you took
as yours
and that's what you need to do it's not
about finding the answer or seeing that
once it's about Discerning it on the
peripheral level and then protecting it
there for as long as it
takes for you to become fully
dispassionate and disenchanted with the
life seeing that seeing that threat that
danger you know immediately seeing the
danger immediately protecting it on that
level being mindful of it allowing it to
endure and then let's say within the
precepts go on about with your life with
a perception of that
danger that's already going to start
resulting in this pression that that
that breathing how do you develop the
mindfulness of death with in breath and
out breath yeah immedi the body bring
the breathing immediately in bring out
but again it's not you catching it
immediately means context is
imperturbable that whether there is in
or out breath immediacy of possibility
of death
endures so that's what it means it
doesn't mean like breathing in I'm dying
I might die breathing out I might die no
if mindfulness of the body is
established strongly and sufficiently
enough on that peripheral level
breathing in breathing out doesn't
matter perception of death remains even
within those
acts no matter how little they are so
that's why okay that's if you the buha
said if that's how you practice
mindfulness of death okay there is no
laps in between right there's no lapse
of that of that context enduring to its
full extent M it's not a full extent if
if it's kind of slightly delayed oh I
think I might die by the end of the day
or the other monk says I'll die by the
end of this meal one says I'll die by
the end of in and out breath and the one
says I think I might die by the end of
in breath or out breath and the would
say okay that's that's the full extent
of the context that can be developed in
breath full breath but again it's not
that the mon who who thought uh might
die day he was wrong he wasn't it's
still the same context of the same death
established on the body of seen
peripherally he just was not fully
developed it's not oh you stop doing
that do it like this no no no just okay
what you're doing in terms of thinking
you might die by the end of the day or
by the end of the meal you just need to
upgrade further and think you might die
even within act within
that so make that context totally
imperturbable until everything is
saturated by it
however little or insignificant breathe
in breathe out that's it and if that
context endures like that within a
fortnite mind will be an
adant yeah cuz if there's you you there
there's no room for passion to hide
anymore everything's been saturated with
it so and the carefulness you know you
see the threat there always yeah then
there's a carefulness that comes out of
automatic exactly yeah the result of it
yeah